<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Michelle's [uncreative adjective] Blog</title>
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog//atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog/" />
    <id>http://michtran.ca/blog//atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Michelle Tran</name>
        
        <email>email@michtran.ca</email>
        
    </author>
    <updated>2026-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Retrospective on 2025</title>
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2026-01-01-Retrospective.html" />
    <id>http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2026-01-01-Retrospective.html</id>
    <published>2026-01-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2026-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
<em>Posted on January  1, 2026</em>
    
</div>

<p>This last year was the Year of the Snake in the Chinese Zodiac.
According to superstition, it’s supposed to be a bad year for me.
I broke my one of my tooth and had to get it removed (after a failed attempt to try to save it).
My team at work got downsized, and I decided to move to the security team.
And finally, although I did reach my reading goal this year,
I was in a reading slump all year.
The best thing I read were <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/244606-the-shapes-trilogy">The Shapes Trilogy</a>
by Mac Barnett and Jon Klassen.
Anyways, it was not a great year personally, but I felt like my personal problems were
eclipsed by things happening in the world
(which I won’t get into here).</p>
<p>As mentioned above, I switched to the security team this year.
With all the vibe coding going on in the industry,
I was thinking that it would mean that secure design would be more important.
So when the opportunity to join the security team was available,
I decided it was a good move to help me develop skills around secure software design.
Anyways, it’s hard to predict where the industry is headed,
but doing more security probably wouldn’t really hurt my career.
Plus I find it interesting.</p>
<p>I started cycling to work because the TTC was a mess this summer.
Taking transit sometimes took almost exactly the same amount of time as walking home.
So I decided to brave the streets of Toronto and go on my bike.
I haven’t died so far, so that’s promising.</p>
<p>We went to Banff and Drumheller during the summer.
Banff was really expensive, but also quite beautiful.
Drumheller was all about dinosaurs,
and a good family trip for young children
(nice desert hikes, dinosaur museums and kitschy dinosaur town).
It’s also amazing to see the geographical diversity within one province,
where you can go from alpine mountains to rocky desert within a 6 hour drive.</p>
<p>The last notable thing that happened to me was that I got a new phone.
My last phone lasted from 2019 to 2025.
The only reason to replace the old Huawei P30 Lite was that it did not support NFC
(for a bunch of virtual cards that I wanted to use it for)
and that my model did not support various 5Ghz WiFi bands that are in North America
(so it was a hit or miss connecting based on router configurations).
Anyways, I’ve beaten my previous record for how long I’ve had my phone before replacing
(which was 5 years for my Nexus 5).</p>
<p>Some goals for the next year:</p>
<ul>
<li>Read 52 books</li>
<li>Attempt to get a security certification</li>
<li>Write a chapter a week (I’m still working on that wuxia novel)</li>
</ul>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Retrospective on 2024</title>
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2025-01-01-Retrospective.html" />
    <id>http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2025-01-01-Retrospective.html</id>
    <published>2025-01-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2025-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
<em>Posted on January  1, 2025</em>
    
</div>

<p>The year was generally pretty terrible.
The economy sucks, and it’s going to probably get worse.
There’s still unnecessary war in the world.
There’s still existential angst about the climate.
I’ve been avoiding reading the news.</p>
<p>Anyways, after a wave of layoffs
and feeling like I wasn’t making any <em>progress</em>
with the initiatives that I’ve started,
I decided to switch companies in the spring.
It was the right decision. No regrets.</p>
<p>I was seriously burned out in my previous job,
and didn’t realize how bad it was until I left the company.
I was sick for a whole month after I quit.</p>
<p>I am amused (sad? dreading?) to admit that I’ve actually started using AI to help me code.
I was skeptical about the technology (still am mostly) last year,
but search results has been getting shittier
and have been fairly useless.
It is much faster to just ask AI the question,
then verify via official documentation or running the generated code.</p>
<p>In terms of reading, there wasn’t anything that was particularly memorable this year.
I was trying to improve my Chinese by reading a bunch of graded readers.
And I’ve got a new e-reader which is Android based,
which means that I can install Pleco to read books.
If I had to choose my favourite reads this year, the highlights were:</p>
<ul>
<li>A poetic translation of the <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/205478817-dao-de-jing">Dao De Jing</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/63029823-ten-ways-to-get-dumped-by-a-tyrant">Ten Ways to Get Dumpted by a Tyrant</a> because it was the most funny thing I’ve read all year. The sequels were meh though.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/59066963-devil-venerable-also-wants-to-know">Devil Venerable Also Wants to Know</a>, fun danmei which is also a satire on the xianxia cultivation romance genre.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/50623864-the-invisible-life-of-addie-larue">The Invisible Life of Addie Larue</a></li>
</ul>
<p>By the end of the year, I also got interested in writing my own Wuxia novel.
It’s kind of fun to write stories again,
especially when there are no expectations.</p>
<p>I’ve been an urbanist for all of my adult life.
And this year, my partner convinced me to go to more municipal consultations
(especially in support for a bike lane route in my neighbourhood).
Then later in the year, we started going to bike lane protests.
The government decided to use “bike lanes” as a culture war issue
(to bypass due diligence for seizing land to build another highway,
but that’s another story)
and will be ripping out some very heavily used bike lanes.
It’s hard for me to not feel like my efforts are futile
and that I should just move to Europe.
And to my NIMBY neighbours who don’t want to add bike lanes
but also complaining about the increasing amount of car traffic
that is routed through their local streets:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>THE ONLY WAY TO REDUCE CAR TRAFFIC
IS TO PROVIDE VIABLE ALTERNATIVES TO DRIVING.
(this includes adding more bike lanes to make cycling safer)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Again, my goals for this year remain:</p>
<ul>
<li>Read 52 books</li>
<li>Fix something related to my health</li>
<li>Try to be less angry. Stop reading the news.</li>
</ul>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Retrospective on 2023</title>
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2024-01-01-Retrospective_2023.html" />
    <id>http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2024-01-01-Retrospective_2023.html</id>
    <published>2024-01-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
<em>Posted on January  1, 2024</em>
    
</div>

<p>It’s been an interesting year of tech layoffs, bad economy, generative AI, endless wars and more effects of climate change
(record highs in many places?).
I don’t really know what else to make of this year, other than it mostly wasn’t great, and that I generally avoided the news
(and X, the site formerly known as Twitter).
I’m still relatively fortunate though.
At least we’re not living in war, I’m still employed and climate change has not decimated my city yet.
So overall, I would say that this year has been pretty good for me.</p>
<p>In the spirit of avoiding things, I started avoiding <em>reading</em> this year.
By the last quarter of the year, I was super stressed from work and started craving <em>escapism</em>,
which meant that I would sacrifice sleep to read some pretty bad romance novels.
I would regularly read a book until 3 a.m which meant that I would be randomly napping between meetings the next day.
So I just stopped reading novels altogether since I’ve already hit my reading goal of the year.
In general, it was kind of a slump of a reading year, with most of my favourite books read in the first half.
Some highlights (in no particular order):</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/61058107-the-staff-engineer-s-path">The Staff Engineer’s Path</a> by Tanya Reilly</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/59366223-the-great-displacement">The Great Displacement</a> by Jake Bittle</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/59808117-ocean-s-echo">Ocean’s Echo</a> by Everina Maxwell</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/50892360-black-sun">Black Star</a> and <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/57339626-fevered-star">Fevered Sun</a> by Rebecca Roanhorse</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/62918341-weather-together">Weather Together</a> by Jessie Sima</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/60850767-children-of-memory">Children of Memory</a> by Adrian Tschaikovsky</li>
</ul>
<p>Speaking of stress from work, I might have been pushing myself too hard this year.
I wanted a Staff Engineer title, changed my job last year to get it, and now I’m stressed out.
Anyways, I’ll try to be more realistic about the number of “side-quests” that I pick up next year.
I spoke at an internal work conference, so that checks off a career bucket-list item.</p>
<p>I’ve noticed search results (from Google, Duckduckgo) getting shittier this year.
But it’s only because I now work for an <em>internet</em> company that I’ve noticed.</p>
<p>I’ve never tested positive for COVID before,
and have generally been very diligent with wearing a mask.
I’ve also being vaccinated and boosted when I get the opportunity.
But I somehow tested positive with COVID for the first time this year.
It might not be the first time I actually contracted COVID,
especially given the sensitivity of the test is not very great.
COVID also robbed me of my opportunity to attend the <em>last Strangeloop ever</em>.
I’m still a bit bummed about it.</p>
<p>I had spent a lot of money and time on fountain pens this year.
I started using a fountain pen around 2015 or 2016 with a Lamy Safari and had most of my pens gifted to me.
My main everyday carry combination for the longest time was a TWSBI Eco-T inked with Pilot Iroshizuku Ama-iro.
This year I really expanded my collection, especially after I discovered Aliexpress
and a whole new world of cheap (but good quality) Chinese fountain pens.
So, here is an updated selection of my favourite pens and inks:</p>
<ul>
<li>TWSBI Diamond 580 with White Rosegold inked with Ferriswheel Press Writing Desk</li>
<li>Majohn A2 inked with Pilot Iroshizuku Konpeki</li>
<li>Opus 88 Demo in Sapphire inked with Pilot Iroshizuku Tsuki-yo</li>
<li>Penbbs 355 Galaxy inked with Ferriswheel Press Stroke of Midnight</li>
<li>Platinum Plaisir inked with Platinum Carbon Black</li>
<li>Majohn C4 inked with Jacques Herbin’s Emerald of Chivor.</li>
</ul>
<p>I also haven’t done much travelling this year.
Planning trips with a toddler is a major pain,
so the only trip that I took was a work trip to Montreal
(in which I returned home early because of COVID exposure…
it was not the same COVID that I eventually got).
Do I wish to travel more in the next year?
Maybe. But I’ve been struggling with the effects of air travel on the climate,
as well as the changes to the way I travel to accomodate a child.</p>
<p>I played a lot of piano this year.
Most of the stuff that I played were “by-ear”.
So, transcribing various nursery rhymes (then turning them evil by switching to minor key
or jazzing them up in the bossa nova style).
I also re-explored my roots with some <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tr%E1%BB%8Bnh_C%C3%B4ng_S%C6%A1n">Trịnh Công Sơn</a>
and my childhood with some sheet music that I found in my parents house
(mostly video game music transcriptions).
I’m always going to be an amateur because I never take the <em>practice</em> seriously.
It’s all for my own enjoyment.</p>
<p>I spent the remaining holiday days at the end of the year backing up some CDs from my youth.
Looking at relics of my past was unexpectantly nostalgic, and also kind of sad.
I also wonder how my child will think about the idea of backing up stuff with CD/DVDs.
In fact, it’s pretty incredulous that this was how I did it back in 2004 to 2007.
It was certainly cheaper to get a set of 50 empty disks than buy a harddrive
(of which, I neither had the skills, money, nor equipment to actually use at the time).</p>
<p>In terms of New Year Resolution, I guess the only thing that I’ve been meaning to do more of is look after my health.
I haven’t exercised, and have been eating pretty poorly.
Exercise will be hard to fit into my schedule (and it’s hard to motivate yourself to do something you hate,
especially if you’ve got a stressful job, parenting responsbilities, and living through a rough economy),
but maybe I can fix my diet.
And I should learn Chinese more seriously by taking online classes.
And maybe also draw and paint more.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
